<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Kittysplit Blog</title>
    <description></description>
    <link>http://blog.kittysplit.com</link>
    <atom:link href="http://blog.kittysplit.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
      <item>
        <title>Webapp vs native app</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;App or no app? That’s a question that is regularly posed here at Kittysplit Towers.  Surely the answer is app! Right? &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/2015-07-app-icon.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;_config.yml&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’re actually pretty sure that many of our competitors (some long dead) sealed their fate by deciding they needed an app. Once you have a good-enough webapp, the advantages of an additional native app are not that great. Let’s dive in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1&gt;The case for having an app&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Exhibit one: mobile users&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Almost half (49%) of Kittysplit users are on mobile devices, and this percentage will continue to creep upwards. If these users are on smartphones, give them an app!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Exhibit two: offline access&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People sometimes go to places with no wifi access (which we would never recommend) where they incur costs that need splitting. With an app, they could enter the expenses in offline mode and then things could sync up once they got back online.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Exhibit three: reputation and trust&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s easier to convince potential users that your product is worthwhile and reliable if you have a large number of installs and a bunch of positive ratings in the app store.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Exhibit four: Push notifications&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Users could be informed that expenses have been added or edited for kitties that they’re involved with. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Exhibit five: an icon on the homescreen&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once a user is constantly being confronted with your app icon, he’ll be much more likely to open it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Exhibit six: bragging rights&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’re a hipster startup from Berlin, so we absolutely need to have an app which we can wave around in smoky bars at three in the morning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A pretty solid case so far. Let’s look at what the the other side has to say.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1&gt;The case against having an app&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Exhibit one: Costs&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;App costs money &amp;mdash; lots of it. Even the most basic app which does little more that say “Hello World” will have a price tag of 5k EUR. Once the app does fancy stuff like talking to a server that number skyrockets to 50k plus in no time. And then there’s the kicker: you’re going to have to build the app twice, once for iOS and once for Android. Yes, we know about cross platform solutions, but they (still) suck.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you build a solid webapp on the other hand, you’ll serve everyone, including individualists who use Windows Phones and other wonderful contraptions. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In our case, money is not the issue (because we have none) but time is. But the same arguments still apply. As Richard Branson said: “Time is the new money”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Exhibit two: developer pain&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Making apps is hard. It’s getting easier, but it’s still much harder than making webapps. Quality assurance is an issue, especially on Android due to fragmentation. Making new releases is also a pain, especially on iOS, due to the review process. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When you update a webapp, on the other hand, every user will instantly get the update and probably won’t even realise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then there’s the issue of development speed. If you are supporting multiple platforms, you’ll need to roll out features on all of them &amp;mdash; or at least ensure that missing features don’t break the product. This will slow down your product development drastically. Again, this is not an issue if you only have one platform&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Exhibit three: Onboarding&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you want your product to grow virally then you need to have a really quick onboarding process. This is exactly what Kittysplit currently has: when you’re sent a link to a kitty it takes 2 clicks to get inside and you’re ready to go. There’s &lt;em&gt;no way&lt;/em&gt; that any app installation plus identification process could ever be that simple. (Actually, Facebook is having a &lt;a href=&quot;https://developers.facebook.com/blog/post/2015/03/25/introducing-messenger-platform-and-businesses-on-messenger/&quot;&gt;stab at that problem&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Onboarding is probably where we’re strongest compared to the competition (coupled with the fact that users don’t need to register). An app would be a big step backwards for us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Exhibit four: offline access&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;OK, here an app wins hands down. Still, consider the fact that being in a situation with zero internet access is becoming rarer with each passing year. When we go on holiday these days we buy a data pack, which was really expensive or not even possible five years ago.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1&gt;The verdict&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In our case, the verdict is clear: we don&amp;#39;t need an app (right now). It makes no sense to greatly slow down our development and exposing our new users to all kinds of onboarding issues for the sake of improving an uncommon scenario. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, there are many cases where an app is the only way to go (photos, location-based background services or anything that relies on sensors or synchronisation). Nonetheless, there are many startups out there, not just our competitors, who would do themselves a huge favor by not putting too much priority on an app &amp;mdash; and maybe making do without one altogether.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 13 Jul 2015 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>http://blog.kittysplit.com/webapp-vs-native-app/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://blog.kittysplit.com/webapp-vs-native-app/</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>The new version of Kittysplit is online</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;This is just a quick note to say that we did it!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/2015-05-launch.png&quot; alt=&quot;_config.yml&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We launched the new version of Kittysplit. The old version, for nostalgia friends, is still online &lt;a href=&quot;http://old.kittysplit.com/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. Your old kitties will continue to work exactly as before.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;New Features&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;#39;s a quick reminder about what&amp;#39;s new (we covered it in more detail in our &lt;a href=&quot;/blog/Kittysplit-Version-2-Beta/&quot;&gt;post announcing the beta&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;New design and logo&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Kittysplit is now available in German. More languages will follow soon.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You can now add incoming expenses to a kitty. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Some basic stats are provided per kitty. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Debts can now be marked as settled.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Kittysplit is no longer hosted on Google App Engine, instead we are running on &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.digitalocean.com/?refcode=b300ef2a9cbc&quot;&gt;Digital Ocean&lt;/a&gt; using Phoenix on Elixir.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Massive speed and security improvements.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Much much &lt;a href=&quot;https://vimeo.com/55624839&quot;&gt;more cowbell&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Any questions, we&amp;#39;re right here for you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So long,
Kittysplit.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 14 May 2015 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>http://blog.kittysplit.com/new-version-online/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://blog.kittysplit.com/new-version-online/</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Kittysplit announces seed funding</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Erdem Cakmak, a first-time investor, is funding Kittysplit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I used Kittysplit for the first time during a holiday in Anatolia, says Cakmak. It immediately struck me as being very elegant and solved a real problem. So today, I am very pleased to announce that I have become a seed investor in Kittysplit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Shareholder Value&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Kittysplit steering comittee released this short statement: &lt;em&gt;Mr Cakmak&amp;#39;s investment proves that we are interactively productizing maintainable products. Going forward we intend to dynamically orchestrate empowered process improvements. In the medium term our aim is crystal clear: to fungibly facilitate cross functional e-commerce.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Holistic synergies&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;I met up with the team and really liked them&lt;/em&gt;, Cakmak reveals. &lt;em&gt;Those guys work really hard.&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/images/2015-04-money.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;_config.yml&quot;&gt;
&lt;em&gt;With the investment I have made in the company, they&amp;#39;ll be able to drink that weird yellow fizzy stuff they like for at least another three days. One of them could also really do with a new T-Shirt. Maybe they&amp;#39;ll use it for that.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr Cakmak owns a Kebab shop near the Görlitzer Bahnhof in Berlin.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 01 Apr 2015 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>http://blog.kittysplit.com/Kittysplit-announces-seed-funding/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://blog.kittysplit.com/Kittysplit-announces-seed-funding/</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Beta version of the all new Kittysplit</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;There is so much goodness in the new version of Kittysplit that we don&amp;#39;t actually know where to begin. It&amp;#39;s been completely rewritten from scratch and after vigorous testing we&amp;#39;re now confident that it can be slowly exposed to the light of the real world. You can try it &lt;a href=&quot;http://beta.kittysplit.com/new&quot;&gt;here right now&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;New coat of paint&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The thing you&amp;#39;ll probably notice first is that we have a new logo. We think it&amp;#39;s marvelous and hope that you do too. Thanks &lt;a href=&quot;http://norakuper.de/&quot;&gt;Nora&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/2015-03-new-logo.png&quot; alt=&quot;_config.yml&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To go with the logo we also have a new look and colour-scheme. Note that we may tweak this a little more before we release the final version, and indeed after we launch the final version &amp;mdash; because we can.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;New features&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Onto the beef. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are a bunch of brilliant new features and even more are coming soon. Here are the most important ones:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Kittysplit is now available in German. &lt;em&gt;Wunderbar!&lt;/em&gt; Now that we&amp;#39;ve introduced one new language, adding further ones is going to be much easier. Next up: French. After that? Italian? Spanish? If you want to help us translate Kittysplit, do get in touch.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You can now add incoming expenses to a kitty. Several people have asked for this. It&amp;#39;s useful, for example, when a deposit is returned to the group.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Some basic stats are provided per kitty. You can see how much the group spent in total, how much you spent and what your total share is.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Debts can now be marked as settled. Lots of you had asked for this feature.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;New tech&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We haven&amp;#39;t just polished the surface. Kittysplit is now implemented using some very shiny new technology: &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.phoenixframework.org/&quot;&gt;Phoenix&lt;/a&gt; on &lt;a href=&quot;http://elixir-lang.org/&quot;&gt;Elixir&lt;/a&gt;. Hushed voices whisper that it could be the new Ruby on Rails. We didn&amp;#39;t wait, but went with it now. We&amp;#39;re also no longer running on Google App engine. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We&amp;#39;ll expand on these topics in a later post.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Can I use the new beta for real-life things?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes! Your data will be safe. Once the beta transitions to the default version your kitties will be right there. We are not going to throw anything away.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;What about my old kitties?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Your kitties will stay on the &amp;quot;old&amp;quot; kittysplit. We&amp;#39;re not going to move them over, because it would be a lorry-load of work that we&amp;#39;d rather invest in other cool things. Don&amp;#39;t worry, they&amp;#39;ll continue to work and you can carry on adding expenses as before. They will continue to work for at least a year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You should try the new Kittysplit &lt;a href=&quot;http://beta.kittysplit.com/new&quot;&gt;right now&lt;/a&gt;. Please please leave us feedback in the comments below or via the feedback function. We got to where we are with your comments and suggestions &amp;mdash; don&amp;#39;t stop now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So long,
Kittysplit.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 19 Mar 2015 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>http://blog.kittysplit.com/Kittysplit-Version-2-Beta/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://blog.kittysplit.com/Kittysplit-Version-2-Beta/</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>We found our domain name using Python</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Finding a name for your startup is never easy. Many requirements must be met. A name should not be too generic, yet it should somehow convey an idea of what your company is about. You also need to be confident that it doesn&amp;#39;t describe an obscure sexual practice in a foreign language. On top of that, you need to ensure that the domain name is free for a sensible top-level domain. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We found our domain name (&lt;a href=&quot;http://kittysplit.com&quot;&gt;kittysplit.com&lt;/a&gt;) using a simple Python script.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/2015_03_python.png&quot; alt=&quot;_config.yml&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It generates domain names from text building blocks and then checks if they are free. Because this script uses the system &lt;code&gt;whois&lt;/code&gt; command, it will (probably) only run on Linux.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can try it for yourself. Here&amp;#39;s what you need to do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;1. Checkout the code&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This bit is quite easy&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;git clone git@github.com:caspii/domainfinder.git&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;2. Create your own building blocks&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This bit is also quite easy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Open the file &lt;code&gt;input.txt&lt;/code&gt; in your favorite text editor. You&amp;#39;ll see that it contains a section called &amp;quot;--prefixes&amp;quot; and one called &amp;quot;--suffixes&amp;quot;. Simply edit these sections as you see fit, taking care not to delete the actual section titles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The python script will take each prefix, combine it with every suffix and then check if the resulting .com domain is free. For example, if you only have the prefix &amp;quot;ilove&amp;quot; and the two suffixes, &amp;quot;money&amp;quot; and &amp;quot;myself&amp;quot;, then the script will check if the following domains are free:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;ilovemoney.com&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;iloveymyself.com&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;3. Run the script&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the easiest bit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Run the command &lt;code&gt;./find.py&lt;/code&gt; and the script will take the inputs you specified in step 2 and begin checking which domains are free.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;4. Rejoice&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You&amp;#39;ll see the output as each domain is checked and the result in your console. All free domains are saved into a file called &lt;code&gt;output.txt&lt;/code&gt; for later perusal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Tweak&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you&amp;#39;re feeling adventurous, change the script so that other top level domains are checked, such as .net or .de.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 13 Mar 2015 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>http://blog.kittysplit.com/finding-a-domain/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://blog.kittysplit.com/finding-a-domain/</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Goodbye, Ubuntu</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.kittysplit.com/&quot;&gt;Kittysplit&lt;/a&gt; was made on computers running Ubuntu. The initial backend and the frontend were written on two indestructible Thinkpads which famously run the free operating system perfectly. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/2015-03-goodbye-ubuntu-thinkpad.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;_config.yml&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was only later that Macs entered the developer fray. However, things have changed. Ubuntu is now being retired forever at Kittysplit Towers as a developer OS. Here we list the reasons why.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Admittedly some of theses reasons are not developer specific, but they are worth mentioning because they illustrate why Ubuntu failed in its wider mission to become a &amp;quot;Linux of the people&amp;quot;.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Too much web developer tool futzing&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Installing all the latest and greatest frontend dev tools does not work out of the box with Ubuntu. Things like Node.js, Bower, SASS and so on need extra PPAs, setting up system-wide  links or using sudo to install what should be user-space libraries. On Mac OSX it works flawlessly using homebrew.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;The installation process is unreliable&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s true that one of Ubuntu’s early triumphs was making the installation of Linux vastly simpler than everything that came before. But then it seemed like Ubuntu gave up when the task was 90% complete &amp;mdash; a recurring theme. Wubi, a Windows installer with lots of potential, was eventually &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.omgubuntu.co.uk/2013/04/wubi-advice&quot;&gt;discontinued&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Ubuntu install process has always been slightly wonky. We would often see the odd error occurring when installing from scratch and, though unsettling, it was never serious. Recently, however, we managed to accidentally wipe the USB stick that the install was actually happening from. How can this be?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It seems that the installation process has gotten more, not less, fragile as time passed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Things are too slow&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For some reason, logging into the system from the login screen takes up to 10 seconds. We’ve tried switching off various indexing services but it only helped only a little. Speaking of indexing, the Dash search feature is incredibly slow too. Comparing it to OSX Spotlight is like comparing a squashed turnip to an apple and mint smoothie.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then there’s the Ubuntu Software Center. It takes so long starting up that you get the impression that it’s being compiled from source each time. Whilst it’s basically a really nice idea, it has got “started but not finished” written all over it, like many other Ubuntu-specific things. Of course, a developer uses the command line to install things, but Ubuntu is aimed at the masses, remember?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;The terminal is crappy&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The terminal is the one tool that every developer will be using daily, so why was this not improved a long time ago?
Opening up HTTP links takes ages (what’s it compiling this time?). Changing the colour scheme is very well hidden in some sub-settings. Resizing the terminal does not lead to a nice reformatting of output. And, last but not least: the shortcut to paste ist not CTRL+V like in all other apps since the beginning of recorded history, but CTRL+SHIFT+V. Totally baffling. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Ubuntu is ugly&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ah, the old “Ubuntu doesn’t look good” chestnut. Of course, beauty is always in the eye of the beholder and just because everyone one else has gone for flat design, doesn’t mean that Ubuntu has to. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, the fact is that Ubuntu looks dated. After several promising iterations on the icons and the color scheme, things &amp;mdash; in the true Ubuntu way &amp;mdash; just stopped.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The font-rendering has always been pretty awful (although this could be an eye-of-the-beholder-type thing). And GTK widgets just look bad, especially since on many dialogs they are misaligned.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And whilst we’re on the subject of looks, it’s baffling that the Grub Bootloader was never styled (as it is for other distros). This is the first thing that a user will see when he (dual) boots his machine. It’s the very first impression and the point where the design experience starts. Why give the user the idea he’s been teleported into DOS-world?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;The Amazon search result debacle&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s fine to make money and to try and monetize your users. But to claim that this feature in any way adds value for the user is just bizarre. Privacy issues aside, how did Ubuntu fail to see that absolutely nobody is going to want to see Amazon products in the search results when they’re actually looking for files and apps. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;General smell of decay and abandonment&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ubuntu feels like a ghost town. There have been no exciting features or design improvement in the past 2 years. Looking at &lt;a href=&quot;https://launchpad.net/&quot;&gt;Launchpad&lt;/a&gt;, the project management platform for all things Ubuntu, one sees that the last blog post was &lt;a href=&quot;http://blog.launchpad.net/&quot;&gt;made in 2013&lt;/a&gt;. Addtionally, all of the Ubuntu-specific projects that are featured on the front page appear to be stale or dead. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A quick peek at Google Trends seems to tell a similar tale.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;text/javascript&quot; src=&quot;//www.google.com/trends/embed.js?hl=en-US&amp;q=ubuntu&amp;tz&amp;content=1&amp;cid=TIMESERIES_GRAPH_0&amp;export=5&amp;w=500&amp;h=330&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It seems that Ubuntu has exhausted itself in a string of misadventures,  bad bets and features and policies that annoyed its community. The ones that spring to mind are:  &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ubuntu_Edge&quot;&gt;Ubuntu Edge&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ubuntu.com/tv&quot;&gt;Ubuntu TV&lt;/a&gt;, moving the windows buttons, &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mir_(software)#Controversy&quot;&gt;Wayland vs Mir&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://blog.canonical.com/2014/04/02/shutting-down-ubuntu-one-file-services/&quot;&gt;Ubuntu one&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.zdnet.com/article/shuttleworth-on-the-ubuntu-banshee-controversy-mistakes-were-made/&quot;&gt;Ubuntu vs Banshee&lt;/a&gt;,  and &lt;a href=&quot;http://arstechnica.com/information-technology/2013/11/canonical-abused-trademark-law-to-target-a-site-critical-of-ubuntu-privacy/&quot;&gt;trademark “abuse”&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People are moving on and so are we. Goodbye Ubuntu. It’s been emotional. (But don&amp;#39;t worry, you can still use Kittysplit to &lt;a href=&quot;http://kittysplit.com&quot;&gt;split expenses between friends&lt;/a&gt;.)&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 05 Mar 2015 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>http://blog.kittysplit.com/goodbye-ubuntu/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://blog.kittysplit.com/goodbye-ubuntu/</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>5 lessons learnt building a micro-startup</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;You’re probably asking yourself what a “micro-startup” is. We call &lt;a href=&quot;http://kittysplit.com&quot;&gt;Kittysplit&lt;/a&gt; a micro-startup because we’re not funded and we don’t make money (yet). We don’t have investors demanding regular updates and we don’t have employees who depend on a monthly salary, hence we avoid a lot of the stress that “real” startups have. Nonetheless, the lessons we learned so far are definitely worth sharing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One thing that will strike you if you read about startups is that the lessons they deliver often flatly contradict each other. This is because each startup and it’s environment in is unique. It’s up to you, the founder of your own startup, to figure out which lessons apply to your unique situation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Onto the lessons!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Don&amp;#39;t be put off if your idea already exists&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once you get over the initial shock of discovering that someone has already had your idea, you will begin to work out how you could do it better. Look at your competitors&amp;#39; products closely and work out what their strengths and weaknesses are.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We were actually a little lax on this front and discovered most of our competitors after we’d already started. I’m almost certain that we would never have made Kittysplit if we had been fully aware from the outset of the range of competing apps and tools out there for splitting costs (&lt;a href=&quot;http://alternativeto.net/software/kittysplit/&quot;&gt;here&amp;#39;s a list&lt;/a&gt;). In the end, we made yet another tool to join the fray, but we made one that was a little better (we believe) in certain ways.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The take-away here is: focus on a few key things which you can definitely do better than your competitors and you’ll have a good chance. And here’s a bonus tip: if your product is simpler in some important way, that’s already a key step.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Put off burning cash for as long as you can&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The moment you start burning cash (i.e. pay yourself a salary, have employees, or pay some other fixed costs) is the moment the clock starts ticking. Once that clock counts down to zero, the cash will either be gone and your startup will die, or you’ll be making enough to take off. Hey, that’s why they call it the runway.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Obviously some startups need an investment to start up at all. It could also be that people will advise you that if you’re not “all-in” you haven’t got a chance. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, ours’ was a different experience: because we’re a micro startup we have a very long runway which allows us to learn, listen to user feedback and improve our product. The longer you put off burning cash, the longer you will survive and the better your product will be because of it. Which brings us onto the next point:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;It’s OK to launch a crappy product&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When we launched Kittysplit it looked OK, but it was pretty wonky. The user-flow was weird, it had lots of quirks and it didn’t work on mobile at all. People began using it nonetheless and they gave us feedback which we were able to react to immediately. This was essential to improving our product.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/2015-2-kittysplit-launch.png&quot; alt=&quot;_config.yml&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, just after we launched, we were looking through our logs and discovered that one of our sisters-in-law had created a kitty for a hen weekend. She and a number of her friends had used our half-finished product exactly as we had intended, all without any kind of hand-holding. It was an amazing moment: we knew that we had the basics right. To put it another way: our core assumption had been validated. From then on, we listened to our users and implemented the features they asked for. This is an excellent way of building the things that matter and not getting side-tracked.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, none of this is new. These issues have been examined at great length in the &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lean_startup&quot;&gt;Lean Startup movement&lt;/a&gt;. What was great was experiencing first hand that it actually worked.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Agree on who does what and how much of it. Then write it down&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is particularly important if you’re starting off part-time. Because here’s what will happen: you and your team will be full of vim and vigour at the outset. You’ll be excited about the new market opportunity you’ve discovered and how in the next few months you’re going to absolutely nail it. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then reality sets in. Things take longer or don’t pan out. Disappointments happen. And slowly some of the team will lose interest. Maybe they’ll have other priorities, a difficult client or trouble at work. They’ll do less and have less time. Resentment will begin to accumulate and then things can get ugly very quickly. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To avoid or at least mitigate this scenario, have an honest discussion right at the very start. Define who is responsible for what and -- very importantly -- how their success is defined. Success in this case can be time-based or goal-based. Then write it down and send it to everyone. It’ll be a helpful basis for difficult discussions that will happen later.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Learn to code&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyone can learn to code. Really! The number of tools, courses and &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.codecademy.com/&quot;&gt;interactive platforms&lt;/a&gt; for teaching yourself to code is growing every day. That doesn’t mean that anyone can code a Java backend module or write a CSS animation that depicts bouncing balls. But anyone can learn how to use &lt;a href=&quot;https://guides.github.com/&quot;&gt;Github&lt;/a&gt; and make a few changes to an HTML or a resource file. With just that knowledge, you’ll be able to edit texts on your website, tweak a landing page or move a button.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’re serious about launching a startup, there’s no excuse for not being able to make basic changes to your code. You’ll increase your effectiveness in the team immediately, reduce your dependence on others and just be able to get more shit done. It’ll also be an amazingly fun and fulfilling adventure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Wrapping up&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What’s surprising is that despite being only a micro-startup, our experiences support a good number of the reasons identified by CB insights for why startups fail. Read more about that &lt;a href=&quot;http://thenextweb.com/insider/2014/09/25/top-20-reasons-startups-fail-report/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/2015-2-lessons.png&quot; alt=&quot;_config.yml&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyway, that’s all for now. We learnt a lot of other things too, such as basic SEO, and the pros and cons of making an app, but we’re going to dedicate future blog posts to those topics. If you’d like us to expand on anything here, let us know!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 14 Feb 2015 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>http://blog.kittysplit.com/5-lessons-learnt-building-a-micro-startup/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://blog.kittysplit.com/5-lessons-learnt-building-a-micro-startup/</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Hello World</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Hi everyone!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the first post in our brand new blog.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What can you expect here? Well, we&amp;#39;ll post sporadically about things that may be of interest, such as: new features, stuff we learned, changes in our technology stack, excuses for why we did things the way we did them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We&amp;#39;ll probably not post so much about evenings where we all go bowling (even those happen very regularly).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also: let&amp;#39;s be totally honest here. A blog is a great place to build up a lucious meadow of keywords
for the Googlebot to graze on. So that&amp;#39;s also a reason why we&amp;#39;ve started this blog.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/hello-world.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;_config.yml&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This blog is created using &lt;a href=&quot;http://jekyllrb.com/&quot;&gt;Jekyll&lt;/a&gt;, a static site generator. The philosophy behind it is explained by its
creator &lt;a href=&quot;http://tom.preston-werner.com/2008/11/17/blogging-like-a-hacker.html&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. One of the many advantages
of Jekyll is that there&amp;#39;s no futzing around with Wordpress and databases. We like simple solutions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And so our first post draws to an end. Help us celebrate this momentous occassion by leaving behind a comment below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So long,
Kittysplit.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 11 Feb 2015 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>http://blog.kittysplit.com/Hello-World/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://blog.kittysplit.com/Hello-World/</guid>
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
